hey everyone thanks for listening to The
Grow Your Life podcast my name is
Jeremiah Krakowski and on this podcast I
talk about ways that business owners
mentors trainers and thought leaders can
get more clients and make more money
than they ever thought possible in their
businesses and that's the goal and the
purpose of this podcast and why I do
what I do is to help you make as much
money as humanly possible now today I
want to talk about something that
as is the case with a lot of the podcast
episodes on this podcast it's not sexy
it's not going to sell a bunch of
courses it's not going to get people to
buy from me and yet it will massively
change how much money you make in your
business if you apply it here's the hard
part about it is most people
ignore run away from hide from and are
hesitant to even look at this area of
their behavior and their life
and yeah it's one of the biggest things
that I noticed that stops people from
being successful and so I would be doing
my audience a disservice to not talk
about this even though it probably
doesn't get me a lot of Engagement and
it doesn't
um
you know light up the crowd
and so if you can go through this you
can have an open mind and you're
somebody who's willing to learn a
strategy that's going to affect you
positively
financially in your business
and it might challenge what makes you
feel comfortable
I think you're going to find a lot of
value out of this podcast now this past
week we did a live intensive and um you
know it was incredible we had the most
sales we've ever had and
there was a situation during the VIP q a
where
I had given some advice to somebody in
the VIP q a
and
you know and they may listen to this
podcast and it may further
uh
upset them let's just put it this way
they got very
upset by my advice
they felt that I had misjudged them
uh stereotyped them
and had no empathy
for them as well as
misunderstood how much of a
expert that has been trained in
marketing
and how
Broad and wide reaching their expertise
and accolades of success have been
and so first off I want to say this is
that I you know it was never my
intention to discredit anybody
whatsoever whenever I give advice
uh sometimes
and let me give some context to this
situation this was not the first time
that I had given advice to this person
they had had joined
over six other
seven other live events that I had done
and had asked for advice in the exact
same area and I had given advice in that
area and so
what I had noticed was a pattern a
pattern in my own life and I'm not going
to share what the advice was
particularly
it's not even relevant to this podcast
um
but I did so in a way that personally I
stand behind everything that I said and
the advice that I gave the person but
they took it in a way that offended them
and they got very defensive
and felt the need to prove and validate
their knowledge and position of
authority
and why I was wrong because I didn't
know them and all of the things that
they've been through in their life
and and my advice that I was giving was
directly related to as I said I still
stand by it
an area that I believe that if if this
person
did not get defensive but instead got
curious
um and realized that my intention was to
help them make a ton of money in their
business not at all to be a personal
attack on them whatsoever
um
that they would actually start to make a
lot of money in their business
and so what I find is is that as humans
it's a very natural human behavior to
get defensive
to feel like we have to defend ourselves
and prove our position and and make sure
that we're not misunderstood and here's
here's the problem when that happens and
I realize this because it's shined a big
Spotlight on my own life and my own
behavior is that we actually become
unsafe people for others to be around
when we do this
because we end up assuming the worst
that somebody else is an aggressor or an
attacker in our life and that when we
respond out of hyper vigilance
towards what we believe somebody else is
doing and that we need to defend
ourselves against that person hurting us
and for instance you know looking back
at this this past situation I think
again I don't know this but underlying
you know the reason why people get
defensive maybe is because they have
felt marginalized and they have felt
overlooked and they have felt that
people have not seen them for their true
worth and so that's painful and I have a
lot of empathy for that
that doesn't mean that all advice is an
attack on somebody's character
and and so what I find is is that now
also not all advice is worth taking not
all advice is worth listening to not all
advice is worth considering uh but this
you know this was an area that uh this
person had actually paid to be on the
call for and had paid to get my
expertise in this area and and because
of this I would
be failing at what the person had hired
me for to have been silent about the
advice that I had given
and it hit a nerve and it and it and it
struck a chord
that
hurt
as a at least that's how it was my
perception
the person
that I was giving advice to and they got
defensive
and and so I'm gonna go back and and
just address this and say that any time
that we get defensive towards other
people it's an area of insecurity and
fear in an area that we're trying to
protect
and we have to ask ourselves this
question what am I trying to avoid from
happening
and ultimately it can be trying to make
ourselves
look better to other people we don't
want to appear like we don't know what
we're doing and we're trying to
maintain a level of
proving our worth so that other people
can see our worth
when we get defensive you know I find
myself
frequently with my with my wife getting
defensive
and it's not it's not healthy when I do
so
when she asks me to do something and and
maybe I forgot to do it and then I get
defensive and and I start making excuses
for why trying to prove my position that
doesn't make a healthy marriage
it doesn't make a healthy relationship
and it's rooted again in my own
insecurity fear I'm trying to protect
myself
there's I can I can tell you this past
trauma in my own life directly connected
to the areas that we get defensive in
and and and I found too that
not a lot of people agree with this
because people are like well so you're
just gonna let me you're just saying
that I need to just take the hits and
and have people abuse me and mistreat me
and just let them do it
no not at all not at all
not at all
would never recommend that at all I in
fact I recommend that if somebody is
mistreating you and abusing you that you
put your foot down and and not only tell
them so you leave the situation you get
out of it you don't press in more to try
to convince them that they're wrong you
actually leave the situation you have a
boundary because you're not willing to
tolerate being treated that way I think
that's the most healthiest thing that
you can do instead of trying to make
people agree with you or come to your
side
or be defensive okay but obviously that
doesn't fit like I'm not going to leave
my my wife because I got defensive in
this
situation with something that she asked
me to do with our son and I forgot or
something like that like that's just
completely nonsense at that point okay
and so these two are not necessarily the
same thing like like if you're being
abused by somebody
you have the right to defend yourself
and to stand up for yourself and to do
what's best for yourself
I'm talking about the everyday
misunderstandings
of
and really what it is it's a projection
is we're whether the person meant to or
not we are assuming that we need to
protect ourselves when somebody says
something and this is an area that I've
had to learn for myself that I need to
learn to let go of that I need to learn
to to not
fight and argue and and assume the worst
and assume that somebody is trying to
hurt me or to attack me and it's not a
safe thing that you know in my marriage
you want to know where that projection
came from it came from my relationship
with my own mother
um many of you know my mom but we my mom
and I used to have a a very sort of
adversarial relationship when I was
younger to where nothing I did was good
enough and I felt the need to defend
myself constantly and to prove myself
and to prove my worth and so going into
marriage I've had to rewire my brain
to expect the best in every situation
and to not be defensive in everything
okay
and so what I found is is that as people
it's natural to get defensive when we
feel like somebody is threatening how
we've always done things or how we see
ourselves or or or
that we disagree with somebody but I've
never found any benefit to actually
getting defensive in everyday
communication
instead I found a benefit to curiosity
you know
I've in the situation that happened the
other day I could have gotten defensive
right back
and said no I'm not doing that blah blah
this is what you did yeah yeah yeah like
you know and then that creates a fight
and so my response was like Hey you know
um I I think I was very gracious in my
response and I just I reiterated that my
goal is to help
people succeed and make a lot of money
in their business that none of what I
say
when somebody is asking for advice from
me is ever meant to be any sort of a
personal attack it's always to help
raise people up to a level where they
can make more money than possible in
their life in their business
okay and so so in that a it could just
be that maybe we we somebody said
something away that triggered us
um again
that's an area to work on work on to
where we're not getting so easily
triggered just because somebody said
something a certain way
I've found that I need to do that I
can't assume that everybody who says
something a certain way to me right like
for instance I get defensive when
somebody says Jeremiah why did that
happen that way why did you do that
why did this not work out
I get defensive inside immediately
but I had to train myself externally
to not go into feeling defensive you
know anytime that there's like scrutiny
in my life whether it's positive or
negative I find that I get defensive and
and and and and and I've had to train
myself and learn you know what
it's not helping me it's not serving me
it's not serving my goals it's not
serving the life that I want to live
it's not behavior that I want to pass on
to my son
instead learning to powerfully
communicate
with confidence no matter what anybody
says to us again not justifying putting
up with abusive Behavior
I need to say that because for some
reason people do seem to assume that
I'm
defending abuse
know my heart and hear me out when I say
that as somebody who has endured quite a
bit of verbal abuse over the years that
is the last thing that I would encourage
you to do is to ever put up with of use
of behavior
we have to learn to be less defensive in
our everyday life and realize that most
people are not trying to come after us
or hurt us and oftentimes that hyper
vigilance is learned behavior because
especially whether it be our family of
origin or past environments that we've
been in or could even be our church or
corporate environment or whatever
whatever that is has trained us that we
have to be on guard and you know I I was
working at a um
I was working with a with a University
at one time where every conversation
seemed adversarial
it started to rewire my brain and train
my brain to be defensive all the time
anytime anybody came to me and so you
might be in a situation whether it be at
your job or your workplace or things
like that or relationships to where you
have to be defensive and you feel like
that and that you're constantly on guard
all the time and it's just criticism
after criticism after criticism learn to
let people
criticize you
without you having to prove them wrong
and I've had to do this myself because
I've realized that not everybody who
criticizes me is meaning wrong and and I
don't have to treat everybody like
they're just an Internet troll that's
trying to be mean to me in in any way
and so in this again
I very rarely actually put up with
criticism from most people who come come
at me and and do that but I don't go
into defensiveness I'll usually say hey
this conversation is over you know I
don't have communication with people and
they're trying to just tear me down
things like that right and and and and
in that we don't have to be defensive we
just end the conversation I think having
a boundary versus trying to prove our
position
is actually the better way to do it is
to walk away rather than trying to say
hey you're wrong I'm right and trying to
get other people to agree with are a
side of things okay
and so I know this might sound
counterintuitive it might even sound
like I'm telling you to be a quitter and
to to run away from your problems no not
at all in fact I would encourage you to
lean in on them again be curious but if
you find that you do need to protect
yourself one of the first phases is the
boundaries
is to not actually accept the
conversation and to leave it if you can
and some of you might say well it's not
possible for me to leave all
conversations great and that's a great
area for you to grow in and realize that
you don't need to get defensive there's
always an alternative to getting
defensive there is
and what's cool is there's a resource
that we can actually use when we start
to get defensive in certain areas chat
GPT
everybody knows chat GPT is one of the
coolest
Solutions out there on the planet but it
can also help us in our interpersonal
skills especially in areas where we
might get defensive so let's just ask
chat gbt this question you know I get
defensive when someone
scrutinizes me
and asked me why I did something even if
I didn't do anything wrong
99.9 of the time
I didn't do anything wrong but I end up
acting like
I did to that person because of the
triggering behavior and me getting
very
defensive okay so I'm describing the
situation right here that I end up
dealing with this is something that I
actually deal with personally
okay
can you give me some strategies to help
me be less defensive in these situations
and to become more curious also what are
what are some alternatives to getting
defensive in these situations okay let's
go let's chat gbt it'll have empathy is
sounds like you're looking to improve
your emotional responses and
communication skills listen we can all
grow in our emotional responses and
communication skills I promise you that
you know and and and the sad part is a
lot of people there's they started this
podcast episode and they quit without
even listening to the end of it because
internally they were getting defensive
as to what I was saying
you know it's sad this is one of the
best ones I I see again for me
mindfulness
when you recognize being defensive
by actually taking a few seconds and and
taking a pause and cooling down in
mindfulness is actually one of the best
things that you can do it helps me a
whole lot deep breaths in breaths out
calm my mind and body
um let's see seek clarification instead
of jumping to the fence try to
understand their perspective can you
tell me more about what you're asking
what's your concern here things like
that I think that's great a shift in
your mindset from defensiveness to
curious to show that you're open to
discussion
you know use I statements instead of you
instead of saying you are accusing me of
this you could say I feel a bit
defensive when I'm asked to justify this
can we just ask this more I think that's
a great way of even saying that is is in
between instead of saying you are doing
this wrong you're accusing me of this I
feel bad but you're wrong say I'm
feeling defensive can you help me here
let's let's explore this I need to I
actually might start doing that in in
some of the moments with my wife where I
feel like I'm getting defensive you know
in marriage is like it's it'll bring out
stuff and you where we get defensive
it's just a natural part of marriage I
think any marriage is where you you
don't feel sometimes defensive on
uncertain areas like that's that doesn't
exist
um
but we're willing to grow and we're
willing to learn and we're we're willing
to get better so I think that's awesome
uh validate the other person's concern
even if you don't agree with them I
think that's great I can see how you
feel that way
uh self-reflection later self-reflect
seek personal help
respond assertively express your
feelings
without getting defensive or aggressive
practice active listening open body
language and then use humor I wanna I
want to address can you describe more of
this response
so I want to know more about what it
means to be respond column assertively
without being defensive or aggressive
assertiveness is communication style
where you express your thoughts and
feelings in a direct honest way
it's about yeah and I think that's great
stand up for your rights and your
feelings and all that
and so but Begin by acknowledging your
feelings I feel this way I think you
know instead of you're making me feel
bad
you know say I feel upset when
State your needs clearly this is one of
the biggest reasons why we don't why we
get defensive
we're not expressing our needs clearly
to people we're not actually asking for
what we want
we're just assuming that the person has
more power over us in that situation and
this is why brene Brown writes some
great books on this topic vulnerability
vulnerabilities when we open ourselves
up
to what we might have previously gotten
defensive with and we don't fight and we
get curious that's where creativity and
Beauty and the magic of Life flows
and so in that
when we start to get curious when we
start also just asking for more of what
we want
and and and explicitly expressing hey
I want more of this I would appreciate
if we could have discussions about this
area that I'm struggling with
in in this way I don't appreciate when
maybe you say that that way to me could
you try something else maybe try saying
it this way I started saying that with
my wife and it's helped our
communication to where maybe she'll say
something to me that triggers me and
I'll say hey this triggered me I start
taking personal responsibility and
ultimately when we can start taking
personal responsibility in our lives for
how we feel our actions our situations
what happens
and we say how did I contribute to this
not who is to blame
we're not looking for somebody to blame
see that's that's a key shift in your
life that's going to shift you out of
scarcity when we stop trying to blame
and we say okay how did I contribute to
this because that's a position of
abundance in our lives
and we realize that we can get all of
our needs met
and that we're not a victim in any
situation
and we step out of the victim mindset
and we step into
living being talking communicating and
operating
as a powerful autonomous person that is
able to make strategic decisions for
themselves
and is able to express their needs and
express their desires you're not a robot
you're not an AI
and neither is anybody else
and so when we learn how to do this our
interpersonal interactions get a whole
lot better even if we disagree with
somebody I can you know I can disagree
with you and we and and I and I have
told people I disagree with you I
disagree with you on that area we can
disagree with people without having to
fight each other without having to be
angry without having to be upset
and we can find common ground and we can
learn from each other in these areas you
know I learned a lot this week by
leaning into some tough conversations
during some of our broadcasts we had a
number of moments where there was some
heated moments where I might have said
something maybe misunderstood something
but we were able to find resolve out of
that
and that's what I want to encourage you
in is to always be curious and never
give up
wanting to learn to figure out what's
really going on behind the scenes
and especially when you can become
self-aware as to how am I feeling in
this situation how did this make me feel
and deeper when did I first feel this
way
when did I first feel this way that I
felt somebody made me feel this way
right
again we know that people don't
technically make us feel a certain ways
but they can influence
and so there can be triggers that happen
and when we become self-aware of our
triggers
by the way
just because I got triggered by somebody
doesn't mean that they necessarily did
anything wrong
that's a powerful powerful thing to
realize that just because you might get
triggered by somebody doesn't
necessarily mean that they did anything
wrong
it might just be a projection of a past
similar situation where somebody might
have said something and you're bringing
Inc and and combining the version of
what you thought
of what you know that the person the
past did to you and you're putting that
on the person now and assuming that
they're the same situation I used to do
that a lot
I used to assume that everybody was out
to get me
and when I gave up the crown of trying
to be so defensive and I also stopped
being so critical of myself and others
and I gave myself a lot of
self-compassion and I give other people
a lot of compassion
I don't think you can have too much
compassion really I don't
I don't think you have too much kindness
but also sometimes we have to say hard
things
and we can't hold back and we can't
tiptoe around speaking the truth to
people just because they might get
defensive and so in that as well when we
know that we also need to work on our
own defensiveness if we're going to
start operating that way we also need to
give other people the ability to operate
that way and that creates incredible
relationships incredible conversations
and situations in your life you're gonna
find yourself in the future if you start
applying what I've shared with you today
you're going to start to find situations
where you were previously blocked in
your life
and you're going to start finding Paths
of learning that maybe have been closed
off to you this is what happened to me
when I stopped getting so defensive and
I'm not perfect at this by any means
whatsoever
but when I stop getting so defensive in
every situation
and I started loving myself more and
stopped seeking approval from other
people
stop trying to seek my validation and
what other people think about me stop
trying to manage and maintain what other
people's opinions of me are
all of my relationships improved my
clients got better results and
everything around my world got better
and so I would just encourage you take
it from me it's not worth it to try to
be a people pleaser to try to please
everybody to try to say everything right
do everything right follow all the
little standards that people put on us I
I get it I understand it and we don't
need to be defensive when people say hey
you should do this or you should do that
start carving your own path
but be curious you know sometimes there
might be an area for us to grow again
most criticism that we get is not worth
listening to unless it's coming from a
source that we know is a mentor or a
coach or somebody that has our best
interest in mind my mom and I this is
incredible I'm gonna I'm just gonna
close this with this
you know she was the source of so much
pain in my life growing up
really was she really was
you know she's also been one of the
biggest cheerleaders in my life of of
getting therapy and healing from some of
that pain that she knows that she caused
and we had a conversation this way this
this week that now she's actually one of
the biggest people speaking into my life
and empowering me and giving me tools
and when she has to come to me and she
might have a a word of criticism first
off I don't have to agree with
everything I'll tell her hey I don't
agree with that I'm gonna probably go
this fast
and it's great we have a great
conversation that's awesome
but I don't have to get defensive
anymore because I know where she's
coming from
she's trying to help me she has my best
interest in mind
she wants me to make more money than
she's ever made in her life
you know that's that's been a big shift
for us in our family for the first time
she wants to see her kids making more
money than she's ever made
that's what my hope and prayer always
was
but it wasn't the reality for years and
now it's it is the reality and it's
incredible and we have an incredible
relationship that we never had and it
all is a because I committed to my
growth I got to work with a therapist
she committed to her growth she got work
with a therapist
and we're able to come together and see
the best parts of each other that we
didn't see before and that my friends is
magical
and it'll change your life all right
listen if this podcast has helped you
share it with somebody pass it on
I know this is a deep topic but I know I
I really felt a need to put this out
there to share this with you and to
unpack this because I think that's going
to help unlock
massive areas of success in your life
then maybe you've been stuck in in the
past
very life everybody and we'll talk soon
have a good one
foreign
[Music]